[Applause]
it's a tough Sport and we saw a lot of
injuries this year this was a very
deeply injured field Tom sulman we know
he's always going to be the best on the
stones given a Level Playing Field and
no injury strategically you need to go
into the stones with a one and a half
point lead over Tom and then you need to
get second place to beat him but Evan
Singleton did Come Away with his first
ever world Strongest Man Podium finish
let's talk about Evan how is he looking
and do you think he's a Podium threat
moving
forward hey folks welcome back to
strength weekly I say welcome back
because I just know that you've been
rewatching every episode we've ever
published in anticipation for this week
I'm David Thomas T joined by the
incomparable the
Irreplaceable the
encourageable Phil blechman and we are
bringing you a recap of the 2024 world
strongest man competition we have a new
old Champion that's the Highlight we're
going to break down all of the action
from the 2024 World's Strongest Man from
South Carolina including the podium
surprises withdrawals you name it it's
strength weagley we're going to talk
about the world Strongest Man standings
we're going to talk about Tom stman and
a little bit about his place in history
because this is his third world
strongest man title he joins some rare
company there and we're also going to
talk about the rest of the podium
Canadian Mell Hooper and American Evan
Singleton who gets his first ever world
world Strongest Man Podium finish what
does this signal for strongman in
Seasons to come Phil it's a Tom stman
Show today he is a three-time champion
but not consecutive because Mitchell
Hooper is the 2023 World's Strongest Man
Tom stman won in 2021 and 2022 back now
at the top of the podium Phil if you had
to describe Tom Stan's performance in
one word what would it be nearly perfect
that's two words I'll take it I'll take
it it's two words yeah yeah and I have
to put a disclaimer because it's not
objectively perfect he didn't he didn't
have an absolute perfect score across
the across the board but out of a
possible 60 points in the final he
scored 53 and to do that it means that
he never finished worse than third in
any of the six events now Hooper was
also consistent the only blunder that he
had was he didn't execute the way that I
think he would have expected he would
have on the medle which is us the Giants
Med which was the opening event of the
final which is typically an area where
Hooper shines he's usually very good at
midline events and and and speed events
and and stuff that uses athleticism like
that is his realm his sixth place
position there was much lower than he
anticipated coming in I imagine that he
would have calculated that he's either
winning that event or getting second
place in that event for sure so and that
was really the Difference Maker it was
one not finish in third place third or
above that made the difference between
Tom Stopman having 53 points and Hooper
in second place overall with 47 and a
half points there is not a lot of wiggle
room and world's strongest man there's
just not a lot of enough events in the
finals for only six events if you have
one blunder it might just be the
difference Baker unless the person that
you're competing against for the throne
also blunders in return Phil let's
actually take a step back and let's talk
about our top 10 finishers here at the
top of the podium Tom stolman returns as
Champion Canadian Mitchell Hooper
finishes in second place Evan Singleton
finishes in third Phil take us through
fourth fifth and sixth as well because
the near Podium finishers can be very
telling and a little foreshadowing when
we talk at the end of this broadcast
about who is going to be a threat in
subsequent years at World's Strongest
Man absolutely if we look back at the
predictions uh strength weekly that we
recorded last week where we covered what
we expected to happen at the World's
Strongest Man there were a lot of
rookies this year and a lot of rookies
making their world Strongest Man final
debuts so one of them is not who be
finished in fourth place that's Matthew
rag who finished it uh last year on the
bottom half of the field and we expected
big things from him we saw that how
impressive he was in his debut last year
in 23 and we expected big things from
this year and boy did he deliver on a
lot of fronts and a fourth place finish
for him here in his second world
Strongest Man final extremely impressive
I would not be surprised if in future
years he is very much a Podium Contender
if you look at fifth and sixth place you
have two more Canadians you have Tristan
ho and Wesley D winsky both of which are
making the World's Strongest Man final
debuts here in 2024 and finishing in
fifth and sixth place at 33 and a half
points and 31 points respectively like
that is exceptional it reminds me of if
you go back a couple of years when Maxim
Buro also of Canada made his World's
Strongest Man debut and he finished on
the podium and that was extremely
impressive going from in your rookie
year to Podium on the world's biggest
stage that's that is a high that is a
career highlight and so to see these two
come in and contend be you know very
close to Matthew rag if you look at Evan
Singleton in third place he was on 36
points so being two and a half points
back and Five Points back like that's an
event or two off like if they improved
in one or two events are contesting
against Singleton in that spot for the
podium like very very impressive on that
on those on on that ad we're going to
talk a little bit about Singleton in
just a bit so Phil were there any
surprises big surprises from the
qualification stages could be injury
withdrawals could be people who just did
not perform uh up to what we expected
and did not make finals uh when we
expected that they probably would uh or
any people that made the finals and you
didn't expect personally I I think that
the story of 2024 world's strongest man
in general is the difficulty of the
sport healthwise there were a lot of
injuries before the competition took
place we saw withdrawals of Matos
kiskowski Martin Le's Alexi novakov like
big names like those guys are Podium
contenders in any contest they run into
two of them are fast Champions and
they're all Podium finishers they're all
multiple time Podium finishers like to
to them dropping out of the event made
predictions a lot easier because if all
three of those guys were in like that
feels like it would be an impossible
task to be able to predict correctly but
they all pulled out because of injury
and then that continued even when the
competition began as well so we saw
Gavin Bilton have to withdraw after the
sandbag steel Chase he needed oxygen
support and he was recommended by
medical to withdraw from the competition
he did we saw Adam Bishop get injured uh
he had to withdraw in the opening event
we saw Bobby Thompson injur his foot and
he had to withdraw so
it's a tough Sport and we saw a lot of
injuries this year way more than what is
common for previous years if you were to
compare them this was a very deeply
injured field uh but on the flip side of
that we also saw a a great wealth of new
Talent come in and and really surprise a
lot a lot of us if you told me that
Austin Austin Andrade was going to have
the performance that he had over the
course of the five days at well
strongest man I I mean I didn't have a
reason to not believe it but I also
didn't have enough support to be like
where are you getting this prediction
from how are you making that calibration
outside of you know uh anecdotal
scouting same thing with ho and D winsky
like they' they've proven themselves on
like strongman Champions League results
and things like that but this is a
different stage this is like the the the
elite from all over the world right it's
the difference between a a world
championship and a smaller Grand Prix in
terms of sizing right another athlete to
take a look at as to where we thought
was going to happen and what is likely
for him in the future was looking at
Trey Mitchell and his performance we
know for sure that the the injury was
likely the cause of like why he was not
able to put up the numbers that he has
consistently put up historically so I I
I don't think that this is a bad
performance for Trey Mitchell or a poor
performance for try Mitchell I think
he's just has not gotten back to 100%
because he was still doing you know
legitimate Feats of Strength that if
anybody you know else in the world got
an A killes te the way he did and then
comes back and is doing what he was
doing it's extremely impressive on only
six months to compete at the highest
level and not be you know squandered in
in dead last every single time like he
was putting up you know impressive
results but it's just not the 100% Trey
Mitchell that we know of Phil let's talk
a little bit about the finals and you
talk about momentum over two-day finals
competitions at World's Strongest Man
how the leader is always advantaged
going into the last day of competition
and we actually expected that leader to
be Mitchell Hooper or at least I expect
that leader to be Mitchell Hooper that
leader was Tom stman by three points
after the first of the finals heading
into the second day and last day of
finals competition the interesting thing
about that is that Tom stolman is
perhaps the greatest athlete of all time
when it comes to Stone
loading and what does world's strongest
man always finish on Phil the stones so
to see Tom stolman take a three-point
lead into the second day of the finals
knowing that it would finish on the
stones where he is almost impossible to
beat I'm not going to say he had it
locked up mathematically heading into
the final day of competition because
several things could have happened but
Tom stman was far out in the lead and
also his best event is always wrapping
up the world's strongest man competition
right we know he's always going to be
the best on the stones given a Level
Playing Field and no injuries so take us
a little bit through day one if you will
I actually got the opportunity to
interview uh Tom briefly after the
competition concluded after he won the
title during all the chaos of C and such
I got to hop on the phone with him and I
actually asked him I said hey man after
the first day you were up by three
points and we know that you haven't lost
a Stones event in your life so like did
you think that you were effectively hard
locked to score your third title I mean
he's a very he was very humble he's like
you know you can never celebrate too
early Anything Can Happen effectively
the summary that you just you just
wrapped up but like if if you're looking
at it from our side where you know you
look at any historical evidence
everybody has everybody else who isn't
Tom has to go into the event thinking
okay the finals I have five events and
during those five events I have to get
as much advantage over Tom as I can
because it's going to be assumed that
he's going to get 10 points on the atlas
Stones strategically if you think Tom is
the best Far and Away on the stones
which is just historically accurate by
every measure that you could consider
you need to go into the stones with a
one and a half point lead over Tom and
then you need to get second place to
beat him that's that's the math that's
just how it works out because if you
only have one point he's going to score
10 points if you score nine points
you're even and the tiebreaker is your
Atlas Stone time so that also favors
somebody who's better on the stones so
you have to have a one and a half point
lead going into the stones against Tom
similarly in qualifying if you happen to
get the unfortunate draw of Tom in your
qualifying Stage Group we actually
talked about this in our coverage the
strategy for any qualifying group might
be to concede the group to Tom so you
don't go against him in the Stone off
because you're not going to beat him in
the stone off so the other five athletes
could collectively just agree that if we
can't get Tom if we can't if we know Tom
is going to secure one of the top three
slots in the group because of how good
he is then strategically it is better
for us to go against each other in the
stone off than it is against Tom Because
unless you win the group you're not
beating him so if you're looking at the
final everybody has to go in with more
points on the stones than Tom so when
Tom has a three-point Advantage going
into day two that means okay we have to
not best him by four ranks over two
events in order to secure a safe enough
uh lead going into the atlas stones and
that's Monumental that's I mean he's a
three-time champion now to think that
you're gonna outrank him in two events
like so the other side of it as well is
when Tom is on his game which he most
definitely was this weekend he has what
we call the initiative which is just
that when you win an event or a previous
event you then go last in the turn order
in the next event and the information
that to be gained by that on number of
reps that you need to hit on distance
you need to go on time events on how
fast you need to go on events that care
about time the ADV the information Gap
is so vast last year when we interviewed
Mitchell Hooper when he won he had the
initiative for most of the competition
and i' point blank asked him I was like
how much value do you put on the on the
leader advantage and he said give or
take five or six points which is huge
huge that's the entire spread of the
podium that's half an event that's
insane that's that's that is that is a
unbelievably remarkable almost laughable
advantage to go into a competition with
and the guy who's calibrating this stuff
more accurately than any other athlete
in you know our time covering strongman
is like yeah it's worth about five or
six points i' I'd estimate so Tom had
that for the majority of the final
because he never finished worse than
third so that that like he had the
everything everything this weekend went
Tom stovin welld deserved I do want to
bring point out one thing that one of
our editors on the Barb Ben team uh
wanted to highlight here um there was
some chatter over the weekend that some
early hand tears for Mitchell Hooper may
have affected his performance and there
were some close-up photos that were
circulating of um some some honestly
pretty gnarly hand tears Phil uh from
what you saw do you think that impacted
his performance at all I think you'd
have to assume that it did without
getting a specific a quote directly from
Hooper you have to calibrate that like
his performance on some
events I I don't think he would shy away
from he probably underperformed on some
of the events that he was expecting to
do better on the first event of the
qualifying stage is the Webster Stones
which like I mean if you could pick the
worst event to start an overall
competition with it's the one that's
just going to annihilate people's act
like the skin of their hands before they
have to then start doing like incredibly
heavy deadlifts and Viking presses and
all this stuff I mean personally I don't
think there's any doubt that HS affected
his performance and I assume that if we
get fortunate enough to ask him about it
in the near future that he would he
would relay that to us as well all right
pH Tom suman's now a three-time world
Strongest Man Champion we have not seen
someone rack up multiple titles who is
not named Tom stolman in quite a bit of
time actually there have been a lot of
single time uh Champions who are not
able to defend over the last number of
years really since Brian Shaw
accumulated uh his fourth title in
2016 we have not seen anyone Beyond Tom
stman accumulate multiple titles now
give folks a little reminder if you will
about how uh the ranks play out for most
titles of all time because we got one
person with five and we got four people
with four and then we start getting into
the folks with three titles a piece yeah
so if we look back at the last person to
repeat uh a title of the fence it was
Brian Shaw as you said and then once
2017 hit we saw a string of individual
Champions you went from Eddie Hall to
hoor bejen to Martin Ley to Alexi
novakov and then you hit Tom Stan Tom
stman is the first athlete in that
string to go back to back before it's
then stimi by Hooper in 2023 and now Tom
Stan's back on top in 2024 and on three
titles he ties Bill kasmire all time
that's quite the company to be involved
in and Tom Stopman is still very young
in his strongman career he's got you
know arguably his prime still to come
which is crazy to think about but it's
relatively true and when in the short
interview that I was able to have with
Tom I asked him this question where do
you calibrate yourself uh all all time
now that you have three titles and I
asked him the same thing when he won his
second title too and he his answer for
both times I asked him is the same which
is he doesn't look he's not looking at
the future he's not thinking about you
know his his spot in history he's
thinking about this competition right
now and he's living present and he's
like I'll take it competition by
competition which You know despite being
a relatively young athlete it to his
mindset he's very grounded at least my
takeaway was that he's very grounded
when it comes to you know standing on
the shoulders of giants so to speak
literal Giants so to speak if he gets
there he gets there but it's not
something that he's currently
contemplating you know like LeBron
Jordan style stuff that's just not where
his heads space seems to be at which you
know I mean is proven effective for him
so far but I would if if if if it's us
if we're talking like where do we put
him Legacy wise I would predict now that
by the time he retires he breaks panov's
record and if you don't mind Phil take
folks through like panowski is at the
top with five has the most World strugg
B titles with five after panowski take
us to the four athletes who each have
four titles yes so then each four
athletes with Brian Shaw and Z junus SAS
they passed the title back and forth
with four a piece during that stint in
the uh in the teens and then Magnus ver
Magnuson and John John Paul Sigerson
also have four titles a piece uh they
were in the early days of world
strongest man and they scored those big
titles and put themselves in the history
books so and then once you go down to
three titles you're looking at guys like
Bill cosm and now of course Tom stman
amazing well that's a bold prediction
Phil we'll have to wait a few years to
see if it plays out that Tom stman
eclipses mariio panowski record of five
titles with six TBD he's got plenty of
competition I know Mitchell Hooper is
looking very hungry uh to get back on
top of the podium but let's talk about
one other Contender the last Podium
finisher who did finish it wasn't
terribly close between second and third
it was really kind of a battle between
Hooper and stman for first but Evan
Singleton did come away with his first
ever World's Strongest Man Podium finish
um let's talk about Evan how is he
looking and do you think he's a Podium
threat moving forward I would argue that
Singleton has been a Podium threat for a
couple of years now and we've seen him
mature in ways he's always been
effective in single day competitions and
the intensity that he would bring to he
when he competes would serve him well in
those environments and then we saw over
the last couple of years him sort of
struggle with these longer
multiple Day events well strong strong
as man takes place over five days you
have a rest day in between but it's four
days of worth of competition and we've
seen him struggle with that previously
and over the last handful of years or
really the last uh two years we've seen
him really mature in how he handles
those competitions in ways that have
leveled him up as an athlete and so last
year was the first year where we saw oh
he is a legitimate Podium Contender
threat that's not that's there's no joke
there at all he's he's legit now we knew
from all of the withdrawals that
Singleton had the best opportunity to
the podium this year that he's ever had
in his young young strongman career and
he also knew that as well we had our
Roger Lockridge our contributor for
barbend he was on the ground live in
Myrtle Beach and Singleton found Roger
and told him Point Blank because He
follows barbend coverage and he knows us
I i' I've spoken to Singleton before
when I was doing coverage the last
couple of years and he said I saw you
guys predicted that I'm going to be on
the podium and I'm going to prove you
guys right you know in his own words
that's what he said and then boy did he
and yeah it's like as you said the the
the podium the top of the podium was
effectively locked for Tom he had such a
lead going into his best event that it
was more or less fixed that gold and
silver were going to be stman and Hooper
the real uh drama was could Singleton
hold his position as the bronze medalist
because he beat Matthew rag on the
overall leaderboard by a half Point rag
had 35 and a half Singleton had 36 that
was really where the drama was going
into the last event and a younger
Singleton a less experienced Singleton
might have you know fumbled in in that
in that spot with all that pressure with
all that adrenaline running through him
here he held his composure he executed
his game plan and we're we see the best
performance of his career and I expect
that trajectory to only continue in
future events we love when athletes want
to prove us right as members of the
media it so rarely happens when an
athlete's like you know what I want to
prove you right love to hear it congrats
to Evan on his first world Strongest Man
Podium finish and if I were a bet man
and I do not bet on strength Sports
because that would be a conflict of
interest I would say uh probably his not
probably not his last Podium finish um
anyway Phil what a weekend what a world
strongest man competition Tom
stolman back on top of the podium the UK
once again takes the top spot on the
podium Mitchell Hooper I'm sure will be
back in the conversation and fighting
for it next year as well a great weekend
even with a lot of in and withdrawals
still an exciting competition stman and
Hooper really separating themselves from
the pack and then Singleton able to hold
on and uh finish in bronze all three
names we will be seeing later this year
in other strongman competition and three
names I'm sure will be in conversation
heading into next year's predictions
because it's never too early to predict
for Barb ben.com I'm David Thomas Phil
thank you for Lending your
massive strongman brain to this
broadcast I can't wait to run it back
next year
[Music]